<document>
  <properties>    
    <title>Migration to RC 3</title>
  </properties>  
  <body>    
    <section name="Migration to RC 4">
    
        <p>When migrating from Unitils RC 3 to RC 4, following change needs to be made:</p>
        
        <p>If no file name is specified for the @DataSet annotation, Unitils will no longer first look for a file named <i>className.methodName</i>.xml.
        It will only look for a file named <i>className</i>.xml.</p>
        
        <p>All uses of method-specific data sets must therefore be replaced by explicitily loading the data set file. So, suppose you have a method-specific 
        data set named <i>UserDAOTest.testFindByMinimalAge.xml</i>, this will no longer be loaded in following example:</p>
        
        <p><pre><code>
        @DataSet
        public class UserDAOTest extends UnitilsJUnit4 {
                        
            public void testFindByMinimalAge() {
            }
        }
        </code></pre></p>
        
        This should be replaced by explicitly loading the data set on method-level.
        
        <p><pre><code>
        @DataSet
        public class UserDAOTest extends UnitilsJUnit4 {
            
            @DataSet("UserDAOTest.testFindByMinimalAge.xml")
            public void testFindByMinimalAge() {
            }
        }
        </code></pre></p>

    </section>
    <section name="Migration to RC 3">
    
        <p>When migrating from Unitils RC 2 to RC 3, following changes need to be made:</p>
        
        <p>Rename the property <i>database.schemaName</i> to <i>database.schemaNames</i> in your configuration files. Multiple schema names may be 
        specified, seperated by commas.</p>
        
        <p>By default, the DBMaintainer will generate a number of XSDs describing your database instead of a DTD. If you want to continue using DTD's, you have to 
        add the property <i>org.unitils.dbmaintainer.structure.DataSetStructureGenerator.implClassName</i> to your configuration with value 
        <i>org.unitils.dbmaintainer.structure.impl.DtdDataSetStructureGenerator</i>. You also have to rename the property <i>dtdGenerator.dtd.filename</i> to 
        <i>dataSetStructureGenerator.dtd.filename</i>. If you want to switch to using XSD's (recommended), specify the path to the directory where the XSD files should be
        put in the property <i>dataSetStructureGenerator.xsd.dirName</i>.</p>
        
        <p>If present in your config, the property <i>dbMaintainer.cleanDb.tablesToPreserve</i> needs to be renamed to <i>dbMaintainer.preserveDataOnly.tables</i>. Table names may 
        optionally be prefixed by their schema name. If all the tables from a certain database schema need to be preserved, you can specify this schema in 
        <i>dbMaintainer.preserveDataOnly.schemas</i>.</p>
        
        <p><i>dbMaintainer.clearDb.itemsToPreserve</i> has been split up into multiple properties, for different types of database items. If you specified this property, move 
        your items to preserve to one of the properties <i>dbMaintainer.preserve.tables</i>, <i>dbMaintainer.preserve.views</i>, <i>dbMaintainer.preserve.synonyms</i> or
        <i>dbMaintainer.preserve.sequences</i>. Identifiers may optionaly be prefixed by their schema name. If all the tables from a certain database schema need to be 
        preserved, you can specify this schema in <i>dbMaintainer.preserve.schemas</i>.</p>

    </section>
  </body>
  
  <script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/urchin.js" type="text/javascript">
  </script>
  <script type="text/javascript">
    _uacct = "UA-2978532-1";
    urchinTracker();
  </script>
  
</document>
